A Guide to the American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) records FA079
Rockefeller Archive Center
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) photographs, 1946-1968, n.d.; 1027; 6.2 Cubic Feet 19 boxes.
  - Venezuela, 4
    - Via Lactea, General, Prints: 47 (Box 16, Folder 265)
      43. A customer from the Maracaibo American colony accepts her daily liter of Via Lactea pasteurized milk from a delivery boy. 44. A cool customer claims her daily supply of Via Lactea pasteurized milk, which reaches Maracaibo customers each morning through a door-to-door delivery system. 45. The sun of Maracaibo already has turned its glare on Via Lactea distributor A.F. Gonzalez, although it still is early morning as he hands this housewife her daily carton of pasteurized milk. 46. A ready customer claims his daily quota of Via Lactea pasteurized milk from distributor A.F. Gonzalez. 47. Trucks line up at Via Lactea's Maracaibo plant. Average daily sales are estimated at 10,000 quarts. 48. No caption. 49. A conveyor belt carries the raw milk into the plant where it is weighed and examined before pasteurization and packaging. 50. Provolone-type cheese is one of Via Lactea's other products, which include ice cream, cream, chocolate milk and buttermilk. 51. Via Lactea milk is a staple at the small stores of Maracaibo. 52. No caption. 53. Inauguration of Via Lactea milk plant in Maracaibo, VE. Interior view. 54. Inauguration of Via Lactea milk plant in Maracaibo, VE. Interior view. 55. Via Lactea distributor makes a sale to a young customer in one of Maracaibo's low income districts. 56. "Via Lactea" milk delivery trucks cross Maracaibo Lake on ferry boats to reach oil camps in Cabimas, Lagunillas, Mene Grande, etc. 57. No caption. 58. "Frosty" ice cream is the latest Via Lactea product to reach the market. Introduced to Maracaibo by Gordon Coats; now VBEC Dairy Foods Division sales manager, Via Lactea improved on the nutritional content of the Frosty product and added it to the regular sales line. 59. Goajira Indian women pose with Via Lactea pasteurized milk catrons. They are reluctant to be photographed. The paint used on the face is made with ground black seeds mixed with grease. On festivals, the paint is usually red and patterns are worked in. 60. Inauguration of Via Lactea milk plant in Maracaibo, VE. Interior view. 61. An American youngster at the Richmond Oil Camp is a happy boy when the Via Lactea milk delivery truck arrives at the camp. 62. Via Lactea had included an ice cream "Frosty" in its list of products. "Frosty" was purchased from Gordon Coates, now sales manager for the VBEC Dairy Foods Division, who introduces it to the Maracaibo market in 1952. 63. No caption. 64. Road sign in "Las Delicias" Maracaibo residential district, advertises "Via Lactera" pasteurized milk. 65. It's Via Lactea time, and this chubby customer is overjoyed. She amply illustrates the fulfillment of Via Lactea's slogan: "Un Pueblo Sano y Fuerte" a strong and sound people. 66. Modest "casas de abastos" are among "Via Lactea's" all steady customer. 67. Via Lactea products are popular in Venezuelan "casas de abastos" (small grocery stores). 68. Via Lactea in the sanitary Pure-Pak container, two or more cartons per door-step, is part of the morning scene in Maracaibo. 69. Via Lactea's distributor, AF Gonzalea, stops to chat with a customer, as he delivers a half-pint of whipping cream, one of the newly-introduced by-products of VBEC's Maracaibo plant. 70. Front view of the "Via Lactea" pasteurizing milk plant in Maracaibo. 71. Inauguration of Via Lactea milk plant in Maracaibo, VE - exterior view. The new Via Lactea milk plant in La Arreaga industrial district of Maracaibo has capacity to place 30,000 quarts of pasteurized milk daily on that city's markets where less than 1,000 quarts have been available up to now despite population increase to 250,000 inhabitants. 72. Faade of the "Via Lactea" pasteurizing milk plant in La Arreada district of Maracaibo. 73. "Via Lactea" milk distribution trucks make early morning rounds throughout Maracaibo city and surrounding districts. 74. Raw milk is carefully inspected upon entering the "Via Lactea" plant. 75. No caption. 76. No caption. 77. About 20 "Via Lactea" trucks deliver pasteurized milk in sanitary cartons throughout Maracaibo's residential and commercial districts and to nearby towns and villages. 78. Mr. P. Moure, Manager of Via Lactea inspects operations in the plant. 79. A modern "flash" pasteurizer handles all the milk arriving at the "Via Lactea". 80. Raw milk entering the "Via Lactea" plant is stored in these large tanks before pasteurizing. 81. Compressors at the milk plant. 82. Cheese-making has proved good business for Via Lactea. The VBEC milk pasteurizing plant in Maracaibo is turning out several other by-products as well: whipping cream, coffee cream, buttermilk, and a chocolate product, named appropriately, "Chocolactea". 83. As the cheese thickens rapidly, it is necessary for Via Lactea's cheese maker to stir is frequently. 84. The Via Lactea plant in Maracaibo, was inaugurated in June of 1951, pasteurizes an average of 23,000 liters of milk daily. 85. House - to - House delivery is a popular service initiated by VBEC's milk companies. An eager Via Lactea customer couldn't wait until the milkman reached his doorstep. 86. No caption. 87. No caption. 88. No caption. 89. No caption.
    - Via Lactea, Maracaibo - Photographs for "Campo" Magazine, Prints: 12 (Box 16, Folder 266)
      90. Cooling tanks for handling 10,000 liters of milk daily were installed on the hacienda "El Capitan" recently by Via Lactea's late partner, Don Deigo Garcia. 91. Close-up of the filtering process which is routine for the 4,000 liters of milk received daily from the Garcia dairy farms in the Perija region of Zulia. This milk in turn is hauled to the Via Lactea plant in Maracaibo. 92. An employee on the hacienda "El Capitan" pours milk through the first four filters (three others are affixed to containers inside the building). "El Capitan" was headquarters for the farming operations of Don Diego Garcia, late Via Lactea partner, who supplied the Maracaibo plant with 4,000 liters of milk daily. 93. Milk obtained from the vast heard of the late Don Diego Garcia, former VBEC Maracaibo partner, is filtered four times before cooling in large steel vats. Through the screened-window can be seen the first vessel into which the milk is poured through a clean, white cloth filter. After passing into the cooling chamber through steel pipes, it is run from the two faucets into sterilized milk cans through first a cloth, then two paper filters. 94. Protected feeding stables were installed by a Via Lactea supplier in the Perija district of Zulia. One of the last plans of the late Don Diego Garcia was to equip his farm with similar roofed sheds. 95. Horses, as well as dairy cattle, are bred on the land of Don Diego Garcia. The photo was taken by Paul Meyn in a pasture of the hacienda "El Capitan", one of the ten large farms Garcia owned in the Perija district of Zulia. 96. A group of calves from the herd of Don Diego Garcia, late Maracaibo partner of the Venezuela Basic Economy Corporation in the Via Lactea milk pasteurizing plant and TODOS commercial center. The photo was taken by Paul Meyn at the Hacienda "El Capitan", one of ten large dairy farms owned by the Zulia capitalist. 97. Farm house and principal outbuildings on the hacienda "El Capitan", property of the late Don Diego Garcia, former VBEC Maracaibo partner. (This scene was used in the composite photo prepared by Paul Meyn for the cover of the Sept. issue of "Campo" which was revised after Garcia's death). 98. Part of the improving herd of the late Don Diego Garcia, former Via Lactea and TODOS partner, at his hacienda "El Capitan" in the state of Zulia. Garcia concentrated on crossing pure-bred Holstein bulls, specially-conditioned for life in the tropics, with the local "criolla" cows. 99. Pastoral scene happily shaped by Paul Meyn at the hacienda "El Capitan", one of ten fine farms owned by the late Don Diego Garcia, former Via Lactea and TODOS partner. 100. A deliveryman for Via Lactea, dairy products company organized by Nelson Rockefeller's VBEC, brings the day's pasteurized milk to Santa Rosa de Agua, a village built on stilts on the shores of Lake Maracaibo, VE. 101. No caption.
  - Slides, 5
    Within each subseries, the files are arranged alphabetically by folder title. Each folder contains a separate, discrete set of slides pertaining to an area of the AIA.
    - Aragua/Carabobo/Yaracuy/Lara, Other Formats: 70 slides (Box 17, Folder 267)
    - Autopista/La Guaira/Maiquetia, Other Formats: 36 slides (Box 17, Folder 268)
    - Bolivar Area, Other Formats: 27 slides (Box 17, Folder 269)
    - Caracas, Other Formats: 44 slides (Box 17, Folder 270)
    - Chirgua/Valencia/Firestone, Other Formats: 19 slides (Box 17, Folder 271)
    - Consejo de Bienstar Rural Program, Other Formats: 7 slides (Box 17, Folder 272)
    - Lara/Merida/Portuguesa/Barinas/Tachira, Other Formats: 29 slides (Box 17, Folder 273)
    - Llanos Region, Other Formats: 50 slides (Box 17, Folder 274)
    - Maracaibo, Other Formats: 70 slides (Box 17, Folder 275)
    - Maracaibo Area, Other Formats: 42 slides (Box 17, Folder 276)
    - Margarita, Other Formats: 26 slides (Box 17, Folder 277)
    - Vegetation - Flowering Trees, Plants, Other Formats: 10 slides (Box 17, Folder 279)
  - Negatives, 6
    Within this subseries, the files are arranged alphabetically by folder title. This subseries is organized by the subject areas within the first four series, and each folder is labeled accordingly. Each folder contains a separate, discrete set of negatives pertaining to an area of the AIA.
    - Agriculture, Negatives: 1 negative (Box 17, Folder 280)
      Corresponds with Subseries 1, General.
    - Collier, John, Negatives: 174 negatives, various sizes (Box 17, Folder 281)
    - Garden Club, Negatives: 5 negatives, various sizes (Box 17, Folder 282)
    - Programa Interamericano de Informacion Popular (PIIP), (Inter-American Popular Information Program), Negatives: 5 negatives, various sizes (Box 17, Folder 283)
    - Nelson A. Rockefeller, Miscellaneous South America Trips (1951, 1956), Negatives: 2 negatives, various sizes (Box 17, Folder 284)
    - ACAR, Eloi Mendes, Negatives: 20 negatives, various sizes (Box 17, Folder 285)
      Corresponds with Subseries 2, Brazil.
    - ACAR, Itau Community Center, Negatives: 1 negative (Box 17, Folder 286)
    - ACAR, Lagoa Santa, Negatives: 2 negatives, various sizes (Box 17, Folder 287)
    - ACAR, Pedro Leopaldo, Negatives: 4 negatives, various sizes (Box 17, Folder 288)
    - ACAR, Santa Luzie, Negatives: 8 negatives, various sizes (Box 17, Folder 289)
    - ACAR, Tres Pontes, Benedito Teixeira da Silva Family, Negatives: 2 negatives, various sizes (Box 17, Folder 290)
    - ACAR, Uba, Negatives: 2 negatives, varoius sizes (Box 17, Folder 291)
    - EMA, Negatives: 6 negatives, various sizes (Box 17, Folder 292)
    - Sao Paulo, Cattle, Negatives: 3 negatives, various sizes (Box 17, Folder 293)
    - Sao Paulo, Hybrid Corn Clubs, Negatives: 7 negatives, various sizes (Box 17, Folder 294)
    - Sao Paulo, Mobile Health Units, Negatives: 6 negatives, various sizes (Box 18, Folder 295)
    - Sao Paulo, Nursery, Negatives: 1 negative (Box 18, Folder 296)
    - Sao Paulo, Personnel (Government), Negatives: 3 negatives, various sizes (Box 18, Folder 297)
    - SASA, Negatives: 1 negative (Box 18, Folder 298)
    - Plan Victoria, Negatives: 50 negatives, various sizes (Box 18, Folder 299)
      Corresponds with Subseries 3, Chile.
    - Plan Victoria, Negatives: 133 negatives, various sizes (Box 18, Folder 300)
    - CADA, MiniMax, Negatives: 23 negatives, various sizes (Box 18, Folder 301)
      Corresponds with Subseries 4, Venezuela.
    - CBR, Andean Study, Negatives: 27 negatives, various sizes (Box 18, Folder 302)
    - CBR, Community Center, Negatives: 2 negatives, various sizes (Box 18, Folder 303)
    - CBR, Farm-to-Market Road, Negatives: 2 negatives, various sizes (Box 18, Folder 304)
    - CBR, Miscellaneous, Negatives: 18 negatives, various sizes (Box 18, Folder 305)
    - CIDEA, Negatives: 27 negatives, various sizes (Box 18, Folder 306)
    - PACA, Agua Blanca Farm, Negatives: 1 negative (Box 18, Folder 307)
    - PACA, General, Negatives: 7 negatives, various sizes (Box 18, Folder 308)
    - PESCA, Negatives: 6 negatives, various sizes (Box 18, Folder 309)
    - Rockefeller Org., Knowles, H.N., Negatives: 30 negatives, various sizes (Box 18, Folder 310)
    - Venezuela Earthquake, Negatives: 2 negatives, various sizes (Box 18, Folder 311)
    - Venezuela, Miscellaneous, Negatives: 7 negatives, various sizes (Box 18, Folder 312)
    - Via Lactea, Negatives: 4 negatives, various sizes (Box 18, Folder 313)